<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
  <!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.28 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-wood-icnrg-privacyprinciples" category="info">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="ICN Privacy Principles">ICN Privacy Principles</title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Stapp" fullname="Mark Stapp">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mjs@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="C.A." surname="Wood" fullname="Christopher A. Wood">
      <organization>PARC, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>christopher.wood@parc.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2015" month="October" day="14"/>

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>ICNRG Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>This document lays out a set of principles that define the privacy requirements for 
ICN applications.</t>



    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>RFC6973 <xref target="RFC6973"/> outlines major security and privacy threats and countermeasures
for networking protocols. It identifies and describes several attacks which can
be carried out against users, including correlation, identification, secondary
use (of personal or private information), unauthorized or oblivious disclosure,
and user exclusion. We refer the reader to <xref target="RFC6973"/> for more details about
these threats.</t>

<t>The authors of this document believe that the ICNRG should share the view of the
IP community which states that passive and pervasive observation and surveillance
is an attack on individuals’ communication <xref target="RFC7285"/>. Consequently, the ICNRG should
strive to meet or exceed the privacy protections driven by the IETF. Moreover,
privacy preserving mechanisms should evolve as Internet security threats and standards
change. This means that ICN should always use best practices for protecting
the privacy of individuals.</t>

<t>To be specific, ICN communication should use, by default, best practice cryptographic
methods to ensure privacy and confidentiality. Presently, this means that all communication
should be protected by forward-secure encryption. We therefore claim that the mechanism
to bootstrap this type of communication should be a native part of ICN rather
than add-on protocols analogous to (D)TLS.</t>

<t>In this document we outline several principles for private communication in ICN
based on accepted best practices to prevent or deter the aforementioned threats.
We do not specify mechanisms to satisfy these principles since that is still an
open topic of research in the field.</t>

<section anchor="conventions-and-terminology" title="Conventions and Terminology">

<t>The key words “MUST”, “MUST NOT”, “REQUIRED”, “SHALL”, “SHALL NOT”, “SHOULD”,
“SHOULD NOT”, “RECOMMENDED”, “NOT RECOMMENDED”, “MAY”, and “OPTIONAL” in this
document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="privacy-notions" title="Privacy Notions">

<t>Privacy has no clear definition. Rather, as RFC6973 <xref target="RFC6973"/> describes, it is a spectrum
of different threats against a user and their data. This document describes several notions
of privacy with respect to specific threats, e.g., information disclosure and correlation.
If we are to outline privacy principles for ICN then we must too have similar notions of
privacy. To that end, the following list enumerates and describes types of privacy with which 
we are concerned.</t>

<t><list style="numbers">
  <t>Data privacy: application data in an ICN message, e.g., the content object payload, is not disclosed or leaked to unauthorized persons.</t>
  <t>Transport privacy: the entire contents of an ICN message are not disclosed or leaked to forwarders (i.e., this information is only visible to the consumer and producer).</t>
  <t>Request (lookup) privacy: ICN <spanx style="emph">requests</spanx> are not disclosed or leaked to anyone but the originator of the request.</t>
  <t>Application privacy: Information about an application is not leaked to unauthorized persons through network activity.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="a-catalog-of-privacy-sensitive-information" title="A Catalog of Privacy-Sensitive Information">

<t>In this section we begin an enumeration of privacy-related information that should
be considered in the context of our principles (detailed in the following section).</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>User- or -host-identifying information.  <vspace blankLines='1'/>
Examples include user names, account names (or numbers), email addresses, source
  or location information, long-lived key names, certificates, or certificate names.</t>
  <t>Application-specific information.  <vspace blankLines='1'/>
This includes any information beyond what is necessary to route traffic
  for a particular application between parties involved.</t>
  <t>Information shared across users.  <vspace blankLines='1'/>
Examples include common group keys or content object names.</t>
  <t>Metadata collected from network traffic.  <vspace blankLines='1'/>
Examples include packet headers and timing information.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="icn-privacy-principles" title="ICN Privacy Principles">

<t>This section outlines a proposed set of privacy principles for ICN architectures.
These are inspired by recent activities in the IETF to prevent attacks such
as mass surveillance in a plethora of Internet protocols, e.g., DNS and TCP.
These principles are intended to be necessary, but not sufficient, conditions for 
data, transport, and application privacy.</t>

<t><list style="numbers">
  <t>All ICN messages should be encrypted by default.  <list style="symbols">
      <t>Rationale: Cleartext communication is not best practice.</t>
    </list></t>
  <t>The privacy of ICN messages should rely on forward-secure keys.  <list style="symbols">
      <t>Rationale: Privacy mechanisms based on long-lived key pairs are not
 forward-secure, i.e., they are not secure if the private key is compromised. Moreover,
 long-lived key pairs can be traced to individuals and can lead to correlation
 and other information leakage in requests and responses. Neither of these are
 considered best practice.</t>
    </list></t>
  <t>ICN messages should not reveal information about the data exchanged or entities involved 
in the production or consumption of data beyond what can be learned from their relative
location in the network.  <list style="symbols">
      <t>Rationale: Minimize information leakage and linkage between packets and entities
 involved in their transport. Moreover, this is to prevent revealing information about the 
 parties involved in a data exchange through their names.</t>
    </list></t>
  <t>Clients should always authenticate an endpoint to which personal identification
information is sent.  <list style="symbols">
      <t>Rationale: Privacy-sensitive information should never be disclosed to an endpoint
 (e.g., a router or producer application) that is not authenticated.</t>
    </list></t>
  <t>Application data contained in an ICN message should only be viewable by authenticated
and authorized parties.  <list style="symbols">
      <t>Rationale: Applications should not rely on network or link-layer encryption
 for protection since the network cannot be trusted. End-to-end encryption between
 the client and endpoint serving content is best practice.</t>
    </list></t>
  <t>Where authentication of clients by servers is necessary (e.g., for access control),
per-application credentials should be used.  <list style="symbols">
      <t>Rationale: Compromised user credentials for one application does not compromise
 other applications or services.</t>
    </list></t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="privacy-in-practice" title="Privacy in Practice">

<t>In this section we describe the practical implications that come from implementing 
the privacy principles outlined in the previous section.</t>

<t><list style="numbers">
  <t>If encryption is enabled by default then only the users who possess the keys are able
to view or consume the data. This restricts the benefits of caching to those consumers who 
are in possession of the correct key(s). For example, a content may be encrypted such that
only a subset of users of a particular application can access it.</t>
  <t>There must be some negotiation between endpoints transferring data, whether the endpoint
is a producer or replica. This negotiation must use fresh randomness to create forward-secure
keys used to encrypt the traffic. A native protocol must exist to accomplish this negotiation
as a prelude and necessary requirement to exchange any application data.</t>
  <t>Application information must be contained inside an envelope protected using some form
of encryption that satisfies the property #2. This does not mean that content objects cannot
carry signatures or public keys, for example. It simply means that such information must not be
exposed in the clear as it moves through the network.</t>
  <t>Clients should never send application data to an entity or endpoint which has not been 
authenticated. Session negotiation should allow endpoint (and in some cases mutual) authentication.</t>
  <t>The observable contents of a message convey no application information. This means that names
no longer refer to objects but rather to services from which content can be produced. This
is analogous to the TLS+TCP/IP model wherein encrypted packets are sent between a client and some
producer POP or CDN. All application data is contained in an encrypted envelope.</t>
  <t>User credentials should not be used across applications. Every consumer should possess and employ
a unique set of credentials for every application they use.</t>
</list></t>

</section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>





<reference  anchor='RFC2119' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119'>
<front>
<title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'><organization /></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
<abstract><t>In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification.  These words are often capitalized. This document defines these words as they should be interpreted in IETF documents.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2119'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC6973' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6973'>
<front>
<title>Privacy Considerations for Internet Protocols</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Cooper' fullname='A. Cooper'><organization /></author>
<author initials='H.' surname='Tschofenig' fullname='H. Tschofenig'><organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Aboba' fullname='B. Aboba'><organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Peterson' fullname='J. Peterson'><organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Morris' fullname='J. Morris'><organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Hansen' fullname='M. Hansen'><organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Smith' fullname='R. Smith'><organization /></author>
<date year='2013' month='July' />
<abstract><t>This document offers guidance for developing privacy considerations for inclusion in protocol specifications.  It aims to make designers, implementers, and users of Internet protocols aware of privacy-related design choices.  It suggests that whether any individual RFC warrants a specific privacy considerations section will depend on the document's content.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6973'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC6973'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC7285' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7285'>
<front>
<title>Application-Layer Traffic Optimization (ALTO) Protocol</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Alimi' fullname='R. Alimi' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Penno' fullname='R. Penno' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<author initials='Y.' surname='Yang' fullname='Y. Yang' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Kiesel' fullname='S. Kiesel'><organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Previdi' fullname='S. Previdi'><organization /></author>
<author initials='W.' surname='Roome' fullname='W. Roome'><organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Shalunov' fullname='S. Shalunov'><organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Woundy' fullname='R. Woundy'><organization /></author>
<date year='2014' month='September' />
<abstract><t>Applications using the Internet already have access to some topology information of Internet Service Provider (ISP) networks.  For example, views to Internet routing tables at Looking Glass servers are available and can be practically downloaded to many network application clients.  What is missing is knowledge of the underlying network topologies from the point of view of ISPs.  In other words, what an ISP prefers in terms of traffic optimization -- and a way to distribute it.</t><t>The Application-Layer Traffic Optimization (ALTO) services defined in this document provide network information (e.g., basic network location structure and preferences of network paths) with the goal of modifying network resource consumption patterns while maintaining or improving application performance.  The basic information of ALTO is based on abstract maps of a network.  These maps provide a simplified view, yet enough information about a network for applications to effectively utilize them.  Additional services are built on top of the maps.</t><t>This document describes a protocol implementing the ALTO services. Although the ALTO services would primarily be provided by ISPs, other entities, such as content service providers, could also provide ALTO services.  Applications that could use the ALTO services are those that have a choice to which end points to connect.  Examples of such applications are peer-to-peer (P2P) and content delivery networks.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7285'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC7285'/>
</reference>




    </references>




  </back>
</rfc>

